hello everyone
so the first question that came up oh
there's something I want to say first
first thank you for tuning in to this
Q&A it's always much appreciated it's a
pleasure to do these and they seem to be
quite popular it's been a while since I
did one but I've been on the road a lot
and away from my computer and so that's
the reason or the excuse take your pick
hopefully it's a reason I wanted to let
you know to those of you who don't know
I have worked on two programs online
that are hypothetically helpful to
people one is self authoring calm and
that helps you write about your past and
your present and your future to catch
you up that's the past authoring program
to identify your faults and virtues
that's the present authoring program and
to make a vision and a counter vision
for your future and to make an
implementable plan there writing
exercises I produced a 20% discount for
all you QA people today so if you use
the discount code August at self
authoring com then you can purchase the
full set of programs for 20% off and you
have a to vie we have a two-for-one
offer so you can share that with a
friend as well so and then understand
myself tom is a personality test site
that enables you to get a big 5 read out
of your personality with each of the big
five traits extraversion neuroticism
agreeableness conscientiousness and
openness broken down into their two
aspects so you can get a pretty
comprehensive view of your personality
and that code is also August and that's
in the description of the video in case
you forget so if you're inclined you can
use those codes and you can try out
those programs we know the future
authoring program for example if
University students do it especially the
ones that are struggling it produces
quite a market increase in their
propensity to stay at university and to
get better grades so the program seemed
very very effective so if you're trying
to straighten out your life then I would
recommend the self authoring program and
if you're trying to understand yourself
better or someone that you know then you
could try understand myself calm
so that's that the other announcement I
suppose is that I've done the two are
now about sixty five cities with Tammy
somebody asked how she manages this
she's exceptionally good at traveling
and very low in neuroticism thank God
for that because it's been a stressful
time with lots of opportunity obviously
and she likes to travel and so she's
very good at helping me manage this
we're gonna hit about 40 more cities 40
or 50 more cities between now and the
end of April next year which is when I'm
going to bring all this touring to a
close in September and early October
we're doing 20 cities on the eastern
seaboard of the United States and then
in October near the end of October about
15 cities in the UK and northern Europe
and then in February Australia and New
Zealand and then in April March and
April then the rest of Europe that's the
plan anyways and perhaps there'll be
some side trips during those times to
other places and so you can find out
about that at Jordan B Peterson com
forward slash events you're more than
welcome to come to the talks they've
been very good events in my estimation
I've really enjoyed them I can tell you
I enjoy doing those talks and I find
them a lot less stressful than talking
to journalists the crowds are there the
individuals in the crowds are there to
come and listen to a serious discussion
about how life might be improved and
they're very very positive events so
I've been very happy to do them the Sam
Harris videos I did for talks with Sam
Harris those are in preparation we hope
we'll have them out in August
everybody's trying to come to an
agreement about how they should be
released it's rather complicated affair
given how many people are involved but I
think we're close to figuring that out
there'll be ten hours of taped talks for
or sessions two and a half hours each I
think the talks were very very
productive we'll see the audience's seem
to react positively to them and they
were very well attended we had 8,500
people in Dublin so and about 6500 in
London so those were very large crowds
so that's very cool
mmm 12 rules for life has sold about 2
million copies now and for those of you
who are mathematically geek inclined
that's 57 miles of bookshelf if the
books are stacked you know as you would
put books on a bookshelf so that's a lot
of books and maps of meaning I released
the audio version of that June 12 2008
een and it didn't it hit the New York
Times bestseller list for audiobooks in
July and August
so that was rather comical given that 12
rules for life was never put on the New
York Times bestseller list so I thought
that was an ironic little touch of fate
and I'm quite pleased to see how the
audiobook is doing if you like 12 rules
for life and you're looking for
something that delves more deeply into
the same themes then you could try maps
of meaning and I think the audiobook
which I read is more accessible than the
written book people seem to be
responding to it that way so I'm pretty
happy about all the positive things that
are happening so okay how am i that's
the first question how am i well pretty
good actually my health seems to have
stabilized substantially I'm feeling
pretty sharp
I have periods of some negative mood
although they're short and sweet so to
speak but I'm seemed to be sharp
cognitively and I can concentrate for
long periods of time and get lots done
I've been able to do quite a bit of
writing in the last couple of months
partly blog posts partly also I had the
privilege of being asked to write the
introduction to the 50th anniversary
version single volume abridged version
of Solzhenitsyn's Gulag Archipelago and
I finished that about a week and a half
ago that took me about two months to
write about 3,500 words if I remember
correctly it was a daunting task to
write an introduction to a book as
tremendously influential and and
important and
and also of exceedingly high literary
quality so it was a daunting task to
write that introduction and I really
wanted to get it right and I hope I did
I spoke by email with Solzhenitsyn's
family and they seemed pleased with it
and so did the editor and I've had a
couple of editors including Greg Hurwitz
my novelist friend from LA who's an
absolutely vicious editor and extremely
good at it so they were happy with the
final cut so to speak so was I so I seem
to be sharp enough to do the work that's
necessary to do I've been working hard
on the online university I've got three
people hired they're all very smart
young guys and we're about a year ahead
of where I thought we'd be at this point
we hope to have a minimally Viable
Product sometime in the late fall I'm
funding that entirely at the moment
courtesy primarily of my patreon support
so thank you to all my patreon
supporters for that hopefully your
monies being put to good use
we'll probably crowdfund in November see
if we can set up enough capital for the
next three or four years I could raise
money privately there's lots of people
are interested in investing but I think
that I'm gonna try crowdfunding because
well because I'd like this to be a
public enterprise from the beginning
Danah have lots of people involved and
we're thinking of all sorts of ways of
getting people involved how am i other
than that
well nonplussed and still feeling rather
surreal about my life I would say my
family's in good shape my daughter who
is very ill is doing extremely well
so that's miraculous as far as I'm
concerned my son's getting married in
September that's Julian and I like his
fiancee thank God for that
and so we're looking forward to that I'm
going on a bit of a vacation during
August which is the first time I've had
off for about two years with the
exception of one week last year and I'm
going to a family reunion in Vancouver
Island and then to Saskatchewan to see
my family I'm gonna do two talks in
Saskatchewan while I'm there one in
Saskatoon and one in Regina and I have a
lot of family coming to the one in
Saskatoon so that and then a little
reunion
after that so that should be cool so
that's how I am and I'm thinking hard
about the next book I have a new book
contract about to be finalized I think
in the next week I'm hoping to release
the next book which will be twelve more
rules probably and beyond mere order is
the tentative subtitle I'm hoping that
I'll have it done by spring early early
spring perhaps January of 2020 if not
one year later but I'm going to try hard
to hit it so that I'm done by next
September I'm gonna write non-stop from
May to September and then I plan to do
biblical lectures from September through
December so the plan is to tour from
January through May essentially then to
write for four months then to lecture to
prepare the biblical lectures and so
forth for four months and so that should
be next year so that's an update
hopefully that's all useful information
I'm very pleased about all the support
it's quite remarkable all this interest
in these complicated matters and
complicated discussions and it's so nice
to see people concentrating on
psychological and philosophical issues
and leaving the idiot
politics as far behind as possible
because it's certainly uh what would you
call it a distraction and a dangerous
one at that so it's so funny talking to
the mainstream media types because
everything they talk about has to be
viewed through a political lens and
although I continue to insist I did BBC
hard talk which was aired today and that
was a classic example of an interviewer
being entirely scripted and trying to
push everything that's happening around
me I suppose
into a political narrative and it isn't
political as far as I'm concerned not
everything is political despite the
insistence of people who feel that the
personal is always political it's like
no there's philosophical domain a
theological domain and a psychological
domain those should be kept the hell
Shepard from politics all right what can
a two agreeable young woman do to be
more disagreeable and assertive if that
isn't how she is temper mentally
inclined oh that's a good question and I
would say first of all that's a very
common question that people who go into
psychotherapy ask I think the most
common problem that psychotherapists
deal with apart from anxiety and
depression is probably assertiveness
training so the first thing I would say
is you really need to figure out what
you want and I would recommend doing the
self authoring program the future
authoring program in particular because
if you want to stand up for yourself you
have to have your goals and your vision
well laid out and well defined and then
you have to have a strategy that that is
matched to those goals so that you can
so that you know what you want so that
you know when you're not getting it
otherwise you're left with a vague sense
of dissatisfaction and resentment and
that's very very difficult thing to
articulate and if you can't articulate
it then you can't negotiate if you know
what you want and you know why then you
can make a case for yourself
okay so let's assume now that you've
laid out a vision and a counter vision
which the future authoring program also
helps you do so you know what kind of
hell you want to avoid that you might
drift into if you were to agreeable for
the rest of your life that would be a
hell that consisted mostly of people
taking advantage of you all the time and
you feeling resentful and bitter about
it not something I would recommend see I
think that women are agreeable because
it helps them deal with infants but it's
not a great temperamental strategy for
dealing with complex organizations in in
the adult world so I think it's a price
that women pay for also being adapted to
have plenty of patience for very young
children and then you have to overcome
that to some degree to put yourself
forward properly in more complex
hierarchies of accomplishment so I would
say once you have your vision
established your vision for the future
and your counter vision so you're afraid
of what will happen if you don't stand
up for yourself then
need to consult your resentment fit
because if you're resentful about
something as far as I can tell there's
generally only two reasons one is you
should grow the hell up and quit whining
so you got to find out first if you're
just feeling sorry for yourself and you
can think that through make a pro and
con case and you can talk to somebody
that you care about about that I'm not
assuming that that's the reason but
that's one potential reason if you're
not merely feeling sorry for yourself
then you probably have something to say
and something that you need and you need
to figure out what that is and then you
have to develop a strategy to to put
that forward I've seen lots of people in
my personal life and in my private
practice not get what they want because
well a they don't specify it and B they
don't ask for it and if you're
negotiating save for a raise or for a
promotion and so forth you have to put
yourself forward you need to tell your
the person you're working for why you
should be treated with more
consideration or respect or have more
resources devoted to you or more
authority
what's shifted to you and you have to
make a case for that a compelling case
so that they have a reason to attend to
you and that's not good they're not
going to notice because most managerial
types are so overloaded with work that
they never notice when anything's going
right
they just notice the things that are
going wrong so you need to make a plan
you have to have a strategy that goes
along with that plan you have to have
articulated arguments for why certain a
certain form of treatment is appropriate
to you and then you have to have the
courage to put that forward and I guess
you have to remember that you owe
yourself as much as you owe other people
you have to take care of yourself like
you take care of other people and and
that's a moral duty and if you practice
that you can do it and a lot of that a
lot of that's also associated with
telling the truth
you know you don't have a better friend
than the truth even though it can be
very harsh in the short term and so if
you're unhappy at work because you're
being taken advantage of then you have
to strategize yourself out of that you
have to learn to negotiate and a lot of
that also means that you have to
overcome your hesitancy to engage in
conflict and you got to think about it
this way negotiation
and conflict are somewhat
indistinguishable and it's easy
moment-to-moment to avoid negotiation
conflict but you pay a terrible price
for it in the medium to long term it's
better to face the conflict forthrightly
in the present and make peace for the
medium to long term and there's there's
courage in that so that's the other
thing I would say is gird up your loins
and and and and allow yourself to act
courageously courageously and truthfully
truth is your best bet if you're too
agreeable so you know you also might
find that you have a pretty good
critical intelligence but that you think
it's mean and so that you keep it hidden
some of the smartest women I knew who
were very very agreeable had
unbelievably good instincts with regards
to figuring out what other people's
motives were but they were ashamed of
their suspicions and really what that
meant was they ended up being ashamed of
their critical intelligence because they
were so agreeable so it may be that the
darker part of you the shadow part of
you knows things that you could know if
you were willing to admit that they were
true and so you have to give some
credence to your to your darker element
I would say
how do you know if you're communicating
with the actual person or a mask I
sometimes wonder if I can ever really
know someone well you can't ever
thoroughly know someone because people
are too complicated you can't even
really know yourself how do you know if
you're communicating with the actual
person or a mask well if you're
communicating with an actual person then
you're actually having a conversation
you know when the conversation
transforms as a consequence of
participating in it and it tends to be
engaging and meaningful if what's
happening is an exchange of ideological
platitudes or just platitudes themselves
for that matter then you're probably
engaging with the mask so if the
conversation is compelling and
meaningful and it transforms as it as it
progresses and and you can see that give
and take that dance like give and take
then you're communicating with an actual
person the other thing I would say is
that when you're communicating with an
actual person rather than a mask the
person that you're communicating with
tends to be quite interesting you know
if people talk about what they know
which means you're really communicating
with them if they talk about their own
personal experience instead of wandering
off into the domain of cliches and
ideological platitudes then people tend
to be extraordinarily interesting and so
that's another good tactic and a good
hint that you're that you're where you
should be when you're conversing one of
the rules I had when I was seeing
clients actively was that if the
conversation I was having wasn't
interesting and if my attention started
to wander then we weren't discussing
issues that were sufficiently vital
because if we were discussing vital
issues then the conversation basically
flew by and so I think that's a good
that's a good marker
what new wisdom have you acquired in the
past few months that you want to share
with us well I've got one I think I
thought thought up a bunch of new things
but this one I'm really happy with I
figured out why you know some of you
know that there's a mythological trope
that I discussed fairly frequently about
rescuing your father from the belly of
the Dragon or the belly of the beast
it's a motif that you see when you see
it in the Lion King you see it when
Simba is being initiated by the baboon
I don't remember fitnah feekiee I think
his name is
after nella humiliates him because he's
still a pathetic adolescent he follows
the baboon I think it's a mandrill
actually down underground essentially
through a long tunnel there's a lot of
kind of scary music in the background
and he ends up contemplating himself in
a dark pool and then his father appears
in the sky and so that's one example of
the reconstruction of the mythology of
encountering your father in the abyss
you look into the abyss and you see your
father and then in the Pinocchio story
Pinocchio of course when he's trying to
become a genuine human being instead of
a marionette pulled by other people's
strings or an erotic or or a liar or a
jackass caz those are his alternate
destinies he goes down to the darkest
place he could find the bottom of the
ocean and finds the biggest monster he
can look at and inside he finds his
father and then rescues him the question
is why do you find your father when you
look into the abyss and I really did do
think I figured this out and it's quite
exciting to me it's such a brilliant
image so we know as clinicians and and
also I would say as sensible people but
there's good clinical documentation of
this that if you find out imagine
someone's pursuing a goal and some of
the things they have to accomplish or
confront on the way to that goal
frighten them and they start to avoid
and then they get more afraid and of
course their ability to pursue their
goal or to accomplish the goal
deteriorates because they're avoiding if
you're a psycho
Pistor even a friend or or a supportive
loved one let's say you're gonna
encourage the person to face the
challenges that are making them afraid
to face them voluntarily and what
happens as a consequence of that is that
the person usually is able to overcome
those fears and develop the necessary
skills and and to prevail and that's
partly because not so much because they
get less afraid but because they get
more skilled and more courageous and so
imagine that if you bite off a little
more than you can chew you get stronger
as a consequence and you do that in the
gym for example when you go lift weights
you lift weights that are a little
heavier all the time and as a
consequence you develop yourself
physically and you turn into who you
could be you turn into more than you are
okay so if you face fears a little bit
at a time fears and challenges and you
do that voluntarily then you become more
than who you are
okay now let's recast that in archetypal
language and make it into a kind of
ultimate so so if you want to become
everything that you could be then you
look into the abyss itself which is the
darkest place that you can possibly
contemplate and that would be the terror
of more mortality and insanity and and
of suffering and of malevolence all of
those it would be like looking into hell
I suppose to some degree and then by
voluntarily doing that then you call
upon the strongest part of yourself to
respond and the strongest part of
yourself is symbolized as the sleeping
farther nested inside the beast and so
the fundamental truth when you look into
an abyss is that you don't see the abyss
if you look long enough it's like the
announcer to Nietzsche's conundrum if
you look long enough into abyss and
abyss then the abyss looks into you it's
like well if you look long enough into
an abyss past when the abyss looks into
you you see who you could become in the
form of your of the great ancestral
figures nested inside the catastrophe of
life and then you can join them so to
speak you can incorporate that and
become stronger and you do that partly
by taking on the challenge voluntarily
and that informs you
because you learn when you take on
challenges voluntarily but you also do
that as a consequence of
psychophysiological transformation
because when you place yourself in
challenging situations let's say the
abyss is the archetype of the ultimately
challenging situation then you turn on
new genes in your nervous system and in
your body that code for new proteins and
you build new structures inside of you
and none of that's going to happen
without the demand that's placed on you
by willing to confront the full terror
of life and so then I would say the full
terror of life is something like the
reality of suffering and death and the
ever-present and the the ever looming
presence of malevolence in your own
heart and in the heart of other people
so it's evil and suffering and to
confront that is really well you risk
blindness by confronting that that's
also a very old story you risk damaging
your vision but if you do it
forthrightly then you discover who you
could be as a consequence and who you
could be is the solution to malevolence
and suffering and so that just blew me
away when I figured that out it was
partly a consequence of having lengthy
discussions with Sam Harris and thinking
this through more and more been pushed
to think it through but I think that's
an absolutely staggering what would you
call it
articulating that articulating that
image fully for me I don't know if I've
articulated it fully but articulating it
more fully really had a profound effect
on me I think that's it's such a
brilliant conceptualization that inside
the darkest place is the heroic ancestor
that whose identity you could
incorporate perfect it's perfect and I
really believe it's true and what it
does is it says that a human being is
actually stronger than the greatest
challenge that can be set before him or
her and that's really something I also
believe it's true doesn't matter how the
other thing that's so interesting about
that is that it it transforms pessimism
into optimism it's like well the world
is a very dark place it's full of
suffering and it's full of malevolence
and it might even be so full of
suffering and malevolence that a
reasonable person could question the
justification of its being as Ivan
karamasoff does in in the brothers
karamasoff which I would highly
recommend by the way that's an
absolutely great book Dostoevsky but the
the truth of the matter seems to me that
if you face the pessimism full-frontal
so to speak then you find something in
you that can that's strong enough to
take it on and that's really says
something about what would you say the
relationship between human beings and
divinity I would say because it takes
something transcendent of transcendent
power to be able to rise above the
genuine suffering and malevolence of
life and I do think that we have that
within us if we don't shy away from the
challenge so you know there's in in the
story of King Arthur and the Holy Grail
so the Holy Grail is one of two things
it's a cup that either held the wine
that Christ drank at the Last Supper or
that was used to catch his blood when he
was speared on the cross either one but
it's the it's the reservoir let's say of
the fluid that eternally nourishes it's
something like that and when you go to
look for the Holy Grail you don't know
where to look because you don't know
where the Holy Grail is and so King
Arthur and his knights who all sit at a
round table because there is essentially
equals each go off to find the Holy
Grail and each of them enters the forest
to begin the quest at the place that
looks darkest to him and that's another
example of the same idea is that what
you and another it's another example of
a dictum from Carl Jung which he
extracted from the alchemical literature
which was in stir Colinas infinite or
which means roughly speaking in fill
that will be found or more to the point
what you most need will be found where
you least want to look but you have to
look purposefully if it chases you your
prey if you confront it then your the
thing that can transcend it and that's a
unbelievably optimistic message because
it suggests that if you're willing to
take on the burden of being with it's
suffering and malevolence that you can
awaken that
with that which is within you that will
allow you to prevail and god only knows
how deep an idea that is it might be the
deepest of ideas because who knows what
the limit of a human being is so well
that's some of the wisdom so to speak
that I've acquired in the last few
months and there's quite a bit more to
and but I'm gonna write all this down
and hopefully publish a bunch of it my
next book I figured out a bunch about
hierarchies too and how they function
and a whole I've developed a whole new
way of conceptualizing one of the things
I was arguing with about Sam are you
with about with Sam Harris was the
relationship between facts and values
because Sam and he has his reasons would
like to propose that we can derive
values directly from facts and he wants
to do that because he wants to nail the
world of values to something solid so it
doesn't float in air and and and and get
let's say what would you call it
hijacked by the fundamentalists or
dissolve into nihilism and and both of
those are terrible ends for a hierarchy
of values so he wants to nail it to
something more objective and and less
relativistic and less less grounded in
revealed truth that removes it from the
domain of fundamentalism and so I can
understand his point and why he wants to
do that but the problem is is that it
isn't easy to derive values from facts
because there's an infinite number of
facts and by necessity a very finite
number of values in fact most of the
time when you're doing something you're
reducing the whole world to one value
and that value is encapsulated in
whatever goal you happen to be pursuing
at the moment or whatever you're paying
attention to which is also a form of
goal directed pursuit and so we've also
figured out that and I kind of knew this
but I could articulate it better now
that you look at the world of facts
through a hierarchy of values and that
hierarchy of values is instantiated in
your nervous system and simultaneously a
social construct because you pay
attention to things of value that you
and everyone else have established as
valuable through a process
of social negotiation and you need to
pay attention to what you think that's
valuable that everyone else thinks is
valuable because otherwise you wouldn't
have any basis for shared attention and
you wouldn't have any basis for trade
with other people so that's another
thing so that's really been helpful
because so now I figured out that you
reduce the infinite world of facts to
the finite world of values by viewing
the world of facts through what's
essentially a dominance hierarchy of
value and that's and that that exists
both out in the social world and
neurologically at the same time and so
that's been unbelievably useful to
figure out - and part of a mystery that
I'd been trying to untangle for about
three decades so that's extremely
helpful and I've also spent some more
time thinking about the proper place of
the right and the left wing so the right
wing basically stands for the what would
you call the the right wing serves as an
advocate for hierarchy and the left wing
serves as a critic of hierarchy and the
right says well we need hierarchies
they're often hierarchies of competence
they're necessary to organize people and
society and they're necessary to get
things done all of which is true and the
left says yes but hierarchies
dispossessed and you have to pay
attention to the widows and the orphans
which is also true and so then the
political discussion is about how to
ensure that hierarchies are maintained
and are functional but also have
sufficient mercy within them to take
care of the people who for one reason or
another are struggling to find their
place even in a hierarchy of competence
and then the necessity for free speech
emerges out of that because the left and
the right have to communicate so that
the proper balance between the the the
current structure of the hierarchy and
its transformation and mercy can be
established on an ongoing basis so
anyways there are three things that I've
really learned over the last few months
and there's a bunch more but those will
do for now
if too much masculine masculinity is
tyranny but the right amount is order
and too much femininity is chaos what's
the word for the right amount of
femininity hmm that's a really good
question I read that a bit earlier and I
couldn't come up with something
immediate but the only thing I can think
of is that often femininity has been
characterized as wisdom and maybe that's
so so the wisdom that God in in the
judeo-christian tradition that God
consults is feminine
that's an old tradition and maybe that's
because order needs to be leavened with
the right amount of chaos in order for
wisdom to emerge the order it can be
blinded tyrannical and dead and so it's
it's the mixture of the right amount of
chaos that turns that order into wisdom
and then that wisdom is often
personified as feminine now that doesn't
exactly answer your question because it
doesn't make the right balance you still
don't have tyranny order you still don't
have order tyranny chaos you're still
missing the proper word there
I don't it's a good question and and the
wisdom idea is the best I can make of it
for now
is it better to marry someone with your
temperament or a contrasting
complementary temperament well there is
evidence on this and basically you don't
want to marry someone with whom your two
mismatched now the only possible
exception to that is neuroticism you
know neuroticism is a good predictor of
marital trouble and it's a good
predictor of troubled period or perhaps
sensitivity to trouble which is in some
sense the same thing it's varied and I
don't know of any research specifically
pertaining to this now I know that
people who are high in neuroticism are
more likely to miss work and to visit
the doctor and to and and to be unhappy
in their marriages and so forth and that
may also account for why 75% of divorces
are initiated by women and I think women
are more sensitive to negative emotion
partly because they have to take care of
infants and need to be more sensitive to
threat and perhaps because sexuality is
more dangerous to women and perhaps
because women are physically smaller and
all of this seems to kick in at puberty
anyways it isn't obvious to me that you
want to match someone with regards to
neuroticism if you're high in
neuroticism I think if you're high in
neuroticism you need to find someone
who's low in neuroticism because then
you have someone around to calm you down
now apart from that the research
literature does indicate that match is
better and you can see why it's hard for
extroverts and introverts to get along
if they're especially if they're extreme
extroverts and extreme introverts
because an extreme extrovert always
wants to be with other people and in
groups and an extreme introvert hardly
ever wants that and that's a very very
difficult thing to negotiate and then
with conscientiousness same thing if
you're really high and orderliness it's
very hard to be married to someone who's
very low in orderliness you're gonna end
up doing all the cleaning for example
that will drive you crazy and if you're
high in industriousness same thing if
you're super high in industriousness and
orderliness you might want someone who's
maybe moderate in both to kind of temper
you a bit because one of the problems
with being too high in conscientiousness
is that you can't stop working and you
should probably stop working from time
to time agreeableness same thing hard
for an agreeable and disagreeable person
to get along you know the agreeable
person will always be the disagreeable
person who won't shy away from conflict
is likely to dominate the agreeable
person quite badly so that's a tough
bridge to - that's a tough chasm to
bridge as well so you look for
temperamental similarity now it's
complicated because like if you're
really really low in industriousness and
you marry someone else who's really low
in industriousness well that's going to
be trouble for both of you because there
isn't going to be anyone around who's
going to do the work so you might
understand each other better but as a
long-term strategy it's no
very good one so it seems like your
message is primarily positive masculine
whereas the positive feminine is not
elaborated with near the same resolution
what do you think um I don't really
think that's true I I think that might
be somewhat true of 12 rules for life
although I'm not convinced of that the
message in 12 rules for life is to find
a balance between order and chaos and
and there's plenty of discussion in
there about the danger of an excess of
both certainly maps of meaning is
elaborated out more with regards to the
positive masculine all right with
regards to maps of meaning is elaborated
out more completely than twelve rules
with regards to the positive role of the
masculine and the feminine I think it's
complicated in part because the feminine
classically speaking is associated with
smaller scale intimate familial
groupings and so
in a world that's obsessed with
adaptation to large-scale social systems
it's harder to make a case for the role
of the feminine we don't really
understand the role of the feminine and
large-scale social structures so and you
know we don't have a cultural myth apart
from Beauty and the Beast let's say that
describes the role of an independent
female operating in the fundamentally
masculine social world and we don't even
know what something like that would look
like and there aren't guiding stories to
some degree because women haven't been
able to do that except in the last
hundred years so I don't know what what
the positive feminine on a large scale
would look like and we don't have
guiding stories for that this is partly
to underline the absolutely radical
nature of the birth control pill and not
only that but the provision of of
technological devices that aid women in
dealing practically with their weekly
with their monthly menstrual cycle which
was also a huge impediment to women and
in terms of interacting in the let's say
the patriarchal world so now women can
take their place in the broader cultural
world and we don't know what the model
for that is so you know you might say
well they should adopt the heroic
masculine perspective and certainly to
some degree that's true but that's not a
particularly fruitful archetype when it
comes to having a family and having a
family is actually extraordinarily
important and it's certainly the thing
that dominates the thoughts of the
majority of women as they approach their
30s all cultural noise to the contrary
so it's something we're still puzzling
out and I suppose I'm still puzzling it
out too I mean with my daughter I tried
to encourage her to be as sharp and is
intelligent and critically minded and
ambitious as she could be
but also letter to let her know that if
she and she she she was always
interested in having kids but to also
let her know that having a family is an
extremely important thing how to balance
that well that is the modern conundrum
isn't it we want to figure out how to
maximize our access to the talents of
women but also to set up a situation
where it's possible for talented women
and and women of all talents let's say
as well but talented women who have
options in the workplace to also have a
family and this is a tremendously
complex problem and it isn't clear how
it's going to be solved you know there
is data showing you know we say well men
should pick up more of the feminine role
and I suppose that's possible but there
is good data showing for example that if
you show women pictures of men engaged
in classically masculine endeavors you
know fixing a roof or fixing the
plumbing or so forth or in feminine
endeavors doing the dishes and and and
and vacuuming that the women rate the
men who are doing the female tasks as
less sexually attractive and so it's not
all on the men with regards to the
utility of them picking up a more
feminine role you know and it isn't
necessarily the case that women will
find men who are more domestic also
maximally sexually attractive and those
things don't necessarily go together so
this is very very complicated so I'm
quite shy and when asked questions in
public I find it hard to articulate a
good answer but will come up with a
strong response hours or days later any
advice yeah I have some advice
one is that or you're probably
introverted a so you're not as verbally
fluent as an extrovert would be and not
quite as fast on the draw verbally but
you know that means you need some more
time to contemplate and maybe you're
high in negative emotion too because
shyness can be a combination of
introversion and high negative emotion
it can be one or the other but but
technically shy is introverted anyways
what I would certainly recommend for you
is that if you're faced with a
complicated question especially one that
has to do with an important decision in
your life that you say I need to sleep
on it or I need a couple of days and not
to answer on the draw I mean I think
that's true even for extroverts I think
if you're at called upon to offer your
opinion about something complex then
it's perfectly reasonable to say look
that's a really hard question I'm not
gonna give you a casual answer I need to
think about it for a couple of days so
the advice would be because you find it
hard to articulate a good answer don't
allow yourself to be rushed and the
second is to understand that this is
part of your temperament there isn't
anything wrong with it it's just it's
it's it's how you're wired so what
causes a person to hoard is it due to
low conscientiousness what is generally
the best course of treatment it's
usually a consequence of relatively high
neuroticism and it's tangled in with
disgust sensitivity as well people who
hoard have a hard time they feel guilty
if they throw things away because the
things still have some residual utility
the best course of treatment is well
behavioral therapy is probably the best
course of treatment
and to plan what needs to be thrown away
and to work with a person that can help
you make the hard decisions that that
need to be made if you're hoarding all
that all that hoarded material is on its
decisions that have been put off so a
lot of that is high neuroticism some of
that can be a consequence of low
conscientiousness as well so the best
course of treatment is to find someone
to help you plan how to approach the the
hoard very complicated so all right
which Hogwarts house would you be in
well I think I'd have the same issue as
Harry Potter when the Hat was first put
on it would think that I might make a
perfectly good Denison of Slytherin so
although that probably wouldn't be where
I would end up so
what is your take on an astrological
basis for significant dates and
religious stories example Christian
religion is a parody on the worship of
the Sun well it's certainly not a parody
religion religious systems as they
expand tend to incorporate everything
that's quasi religious in the culture
and there's certainly no shortage of
solar symbolism in Christianity I mean
it's not Floop that that Christ is the
Sun and there are 12 disciples just like
there are 12 astrological houses and
it's not fluke that the birth of Christ
takes place essentially at the same time
as as as the shortest day of the year
and the rebirth of the Sun all of these
things line up now whether that
synchronicity or whether it's the
attempt by the collective imagination of
human beings to align everything under a
single truth that's a very difficult
thing to say or maybe there's a single
truth at work but the idea that
Christian religion is a parody on the
worship of the Sun is not is definitely
not the case it's more like its
incorporated elements of the worship of
the Sun over thousands and thousands of
years and that's a very complicated
issue if you're interested in that you
could read I on a IO n it's book by Carl
Jung which is like the most terrifying
book I've ever read and so you could
there's a deeper analysis of the
relationship between astrological
speculation and and the emergence of
complex religious stories so
my brother 29 is sick at home with
burnout he's a perfectionist has anxiety
has trouble dealing with stress how can
I help him become stronger well you
could encourage him to go talk to a
therapist you could tell him to go find
broadly make an appointment with three
of them go talk to each one for an hour
and if he likes one of them and he finds
one who listens then he can go back a
couple more times but it isn't gonna
hurt him to go once at least to go talk
it's also possible that he needs someone
to talk to him about medication you know
antidepressants if he's in real trouble
antidepressants are often very helpful
to people not always but often and so
that is a lot better taking an
antidepressant beats the hell out of
being sick at home with burnout and it's
attended dangerous cognitive dangers
dangers of stress-induced illness
dangers of suicidal ideation all that
sort of thing
I would also recommend that he tried the
self authoring program if he's at home
he can write about his past he could
write about his present he can write
about his future he can do a bad job he
can do it over days I think that I mean
we have evidence that the program is
extremely helpful to people and there's
evidence from other researchers that
such programs really help so that would
that would be something that he could do
while he's sitting at home and it's not
gonna hurt him
going over some of the more complex
material might make him feel slightly
worse in the short term but the
long-term payoff is very very high so
that's what I would recommend encourage
him to go talk to somebody he and he
needs to make the plan he needs to come
to terms with what's happened to him and
he needs to make a plan and he might
need to talk to somebody for a long time
to figure out what the hell's going on
you know and we also don't want to rule
out neither does he the possibility that
there's something physical wrong you
know because there's increasing evidence
that the depressive disorders and that
would include anxiety are a consequence
of such conditions as as generalized
inflammation and that's really worth
looking into so I think a lot of the
things that we think are psychological
have a more pronounced physical basis so
yeah
how do you dress so well any tips well
you know thank you I started buying nice
clothes let's say this year really I had
some decent suits before that I did some
research online to find out who good
suit manufacturers where you can look
that up but in before this tour I went
and talked to a good tailor expensive
place I felt terrible spending so much
money on clothing but I felt that if I
was going to go talk to it's been 200
thousand people that I was going to do
it right and and I was going to invest
in some decent clothes and even though
it it hurt my cheap northern Alberta
soul to do it it was definitely worth it
so you go talk to someone who knows what
they're doing go talk to an actual
tailor and and and you can do some
research online there's lots of
resources online that are devoted
towards devoted to helping them figure
out how to dress three-piece suits look
really good I've got them tailored and
fitted so they're not bespoke suits
they're off the rack but they've been
tailored and that makes a big difference
all these subtle things that tailors do
they tuck it in around the waist they
cut it to your body all of those things
help it's really good to have a good
pair of shoes a couple of nice ties I
learned how to tie our full wins or not
recently and that actually helps don't
want your tie to look too skinny lots of
people have been dressing up to come to
my talk so it's nice to see a lot of
young men come well-dressed often in
three-piece suits but not always and
it's really good to see them dressed
like grown-ups I think that's a real
plus I had a rule that I didn't write in
12 rules which was dressed like the
person you want to be that's I kind of
took that from Carl from from Nietzsche
because Nietzsche said every great man
is an actor of his own ideal so very
nice aphorism and basically what it
meant was that sometimes you have to act
out what you want to be before you
become it you have to pretend it's not a
lie it's really
pretense like children pretend to be a
father before they grow up and become a
father it's a form of practice and so
tip one might be figure out who you want
to be tip two might be well then dressed
like that person that's a good start and
because I think if you want to become
who you want to be then no detail is too
small to overlook and certainly it isn't
exactly that people judge you by their
clothes by your clothes although they do
to some degree it's that if whatever you
can have going for you you might as well
have going for you that's how it looks
to me and certainly my experience has
been that the response to my improved
wardrobe has indicated that the
investment was clearly worth it
indisputably and clearly worth it and
it's nice to be dressed sharply to go in
front of an audience it's a sign of
respect to the audience there's other
ways of showing respect to an audience
but that's certainly one and so it's
been extraordinarily worthwhile I would
say if you're going for a job interview
if you're out any critical point in your
life then you should dress the part
because you want to do everything you
can to tip the scales in not in your
favor exactly but in favor of having the
right thing happen so you have written
an article on how to write can you do
the same on how to speak well I suppose
I could I could tell you a little bit
about it if you're gonna speak about
something you need to know a lot about
it you need to know three or four times
as much as you're gonna speak about at
minimum so first of all you have to do
your background research you have to
have multiple stories at hand that you
can use to illustrate your point and you
have to have a point you have to
organize what you're talking about
around a problem so before I go onstage
to speak on my tour I always sit for
half an hour some of which involves
usually about five minutes of anxiety
and I think okay there's a problem I'm
trying to address tonight a central
problem or a theme what is it might be
courage it might be responsibility it
might be meaning
I think and that serves as an organizing
principle so that would be the point and
then basically I organize say a dozen
stories around that and I can kind of
arrange them in it as a journey and it's
a journey that circles the main point
and so I'm trying to explore it to say
what I think about courage let's say but
to take what I'm thinking farther than
I've taken it already and so that I can
plot out you know little five-minute
stories that I have that are associated
with courage and then I can talk to the
audience and I would say talk about what
you know use your personal experience
because that's that's something that
you're actually a master of you can
bring in other material but it has to be
tied to the real world through your own
experience otherwise it's not real it's
also very good to speak directly to the
audience to the individuals in the
audience because I'm always looking at a
single person one after another and
focusing on them and talking to them
just like you'd have a conversation with
someone and that way I can see if
they're following along and I'm always
listening to the audience what I really
like to hear from the audience is no
noise at all silence because if the
audience especially you know if it's a
couple hundred or a couple of thousand
people if the audience is dead silent
then I know that I'm on the right track
and so the other thing I would say is
you're telling stories so every fact
that you relate or every set of facts
has to be tied to a story there has to
be a meaningful output which is
something like why is it important to
your life that you know this fact how is
it related to how you're going to
conduct yourself moving forward or how
are you going to see the world so
because that's kind of the essence of
meaning how does this fact change the
way you perceive the world or act in the
world that's the meaning of the fact and
facts without meaning are dull so you
need to know that you need to tell the
truth that's for sure and and and I mean
for me my talks are really
they're an attempt to explore a set of
ideas in the most truthful way that I
can manage and that's also an adventure
because letting yourself speak freely
about a topic you don't always know
where it's gonna go and so but that also
hooks in the audience because they're
not there along for the ride right and
there's a risk that risk is you might
forget where you are you might lose the
thread you might say something you
regret you might get confused and it's
this the talk should be a process of
exploration like a journey that you're
taking the audience along on it's the
same when you're reading a novel like a
great novel isn't exactly plotted out
from beginning to end to begin with the
author is taking himself or herself and
you on an intellectual adventure through
the through the character development
and the characters have to be allowed to
live and to express themselves and the
novel needs to unfold it's like a
colloquy between the conscious mind and
the unconscious source of inspiration
and the novel is actually a journey
through a characterological landscape
and the author shouldn't know where he
or she's going to end up at the
beginning same with an artist and who's
writing a song or a piece of music or a
piece of visual art there has to be play
and exploration along the way and so you
also don't want to deliver and
over-prepared talk in my estimation or
at least that's not how I do it you want
to have a theme you want to have a body
of knowledge from which you can draw on
and then you want to be actively
exploring the idea in front of the
audience and that's very gripping for
everyone including you and so and you
should learn something from the talk
it's an opportunity to think on your
feet and anyways that's my style of
lecturing it's it's a trapeze act
without a safety net I would say and
that's part of what makes it gripping is
that there's a high probability of
failure and I would say with any
performance that's going to be gripping
that on the edge of the seat gripping
there has to be a high probability of
failure and that's why I don't speak
with notes if you speak with notes which
you might
have to if you're a beginning speaker
then you cannot fail because you can
always read the notes and so there's a
there's a net you'll fall in the net but
you won't die but you'll never do
anything spectacular so that's the thing
is if you're gonna do something
spectacular you have to take the risk
and if you're gonna take the risk you
have to think on your feet and then you
also have to have something to think
about you have to be been working on
this material you know I've been working
on this stuff I talk about for 30 years
for tens of thousands of hours and so I
have that reservoir of knowledge I
suppose and you know whenever I read
something new I'm slotting it into the
knowledge structure that I used to
generate my talks and I'm reading all
the time and lots of the things I read I
forget they're not relevant to my
central mission whatever that happens to
be looks like some it looks something
like the delineation of the relationship
between responsibilities and meaning and
and maybe responsibilities meaning and
perception it's something like that and
so I have a central concern or deeper
than that in some sense my central
concern was how to ensure personally
that if I was tempted in a situation
like the situations that arose in the
Soviet Union and Nazi Germany that I
wouldn't fall prey to those totalitarian
systems and act in the reprehensible
manner that so many people acted in
that's really been a driving concern of
mine and and that's bleeds over into the
relationship between meaning and
responsibility and perception so there's
a core set of problems that I'm working
on and every talk is an attempt to
further develop those so you also have
to have a problem you know you think
well you don't want to have a problem
it's like yeah you do you want to you
want to you've got problems anyways if
you're alive you've got problems pick
one of them it can be your problem and
that can be the problem you try to
address whatever that happens to be and
then you have something to talk about
how am I going to address this problem
how can this problem be addressed so you
need to have a problem to if you're
gonna talk just like you need to have a
problem if you're gonna write because
the writing is an attempt to solve the
problem and so is there talking if
you're not trying to solve a problem
what the hell are you doing talking
why should anyone care it's got to be a
real problem to like a you know a
nail-biter of a problem a dragon of a
problem and if it's a problem that
everyone else shares so much the better
so and then you grapple with it so
thoughts on the Eastern idea of moving
away from excessive thinking into the
awareness beyond thinking removing it
from the driver's seat to be used more
as a tool yeah well I thought a lot
about this in relationship to a couple
of ancient ideas the one Mesopotamian
idea characterization of Marduk who is
the highest Mesopotamian deity
it was Marduk who carved up the goddess
of chaos time out into pieces and made
the world out of her pieces so Marduk is
the force that confronts chaos and
builds habitable order like the logos in
Genesis and one of marducks attributes
was that he had eyes all the way around
his head and that he could speak magic
words
those two attributes but it's the eyes
that are most crucial importance with
regard to this question
then there's Horus the Egyptian god
who's the famous AI and Horus is really
a what a day off' occation of attention
I would say and there's a difference
between attention and thinking like let
me let me give you an example so
thinking seems to be instrumental mostly
so if you think people also often say to
me well what's your what's your strategy
when you go into an interview and the
answer is well I don't have a strategy
when I go into an interview because I'm
there to have a conversation and I'm not
sure where the conversation will go and
I'm willing to let it go wherever it
goes I'm not there to sell books
although I'm perfectly happy if more
books sell because well because of
obviously I wrote a book and I want
people to read it and there's a whole
enterprise behind it and so it's also my
responsibility to do the marketing
properly but I'm not going to do these
interviews to sell books or to promote
myself or or it I don't have a strategic
goal in mind
except that I'm going to have a
conversation and I'm going to say what I
think and and and take the consequences
because I assume that if I say something
and I believe it's true then the
consequences are as positive as they can
be regardless of how they look at the
time and that's an issue of faith
because I believe that the habitable
order is generated by spoken truth I
believe that I think that's the truest
that's the truest thing I know and so
and so I go into the interview and I did
this in my clinical practice and I try
to do this when I'm talking to people to
is that I'm not thinking about where the
conversation is going or what point I
want to make or what I want the outcome
to be any of that I just let that go
you know it's within this broader
framework of assuming that the truth is
the most effective means of progressing
and then I pay attention and what
happens when you pay attention is that
while you're watching a person this is a
great treatment for social anxiety by
the way because if you're socially
anxious you tend not to pay attention to
the person pay attention to who you're
talking to watch them like a hawk like
not paranoid or anything like that and
not too intently because you make them
uncomfortable but intently pay attention
to what they're saying to how they look
to their facial gestures all of that
look at their face and watch and listen
and try to understand what they're
saying and what you'll see is that well
questions pop into your minds like well
I didn't understand what you said can
you clarify that and sounds like you
mean this is this what you mean but not
in a I'll put you on the spot because I
think you're wrong sort of way but in a
clarification sort of way and all of
that attention and so what I'm doing
clinical work with people this is the
reason I quit by the way about a year
ago is because I was starting to get
distracted I had a rule which was you
have an hour with me and I do nothing
but pay attention to you I'm not
thinking about what I want to accomplish
I'm not thinking about the problems in
my life not distracted and I listen to
you and I ask questions when I don't
understand and if a thought occurs to me
while I'm paying attention to you then
I'll tell you what it is you see and
that's that's
using awareness primarily and thinking
secondarily like I don't think well
here's what I want to cure this person
and I'm going to maneuver them into
certain responses by using these
communicative tools I think I'm going to
pay attention to this person we're going
to discuss where we're going and why I'm
going to listen to what they say and
then when they're talking things are
going to occur within me I'm gonna see
images and thoughts are going to emerge
from the background and then I'll share
them not always because I usually have
more thoughts than can be shared but if
a thought comes up and it seems like an
interesting reaction to what the person
just said then I'll just tell them and
sort of without commitment to it and
it's usually okay you just said this and
so this question emerged so we need to
straighten that out because I'm confused
or you said this and I had this image or
you said this and this thought came to
mind and it seems to be this is this so
that's one person's reaction to the way
that you're conducting yourself at the
moment so thinking is instrumental I
outlined this in I think it's rule 7 do
what is meaningful not what is expedient
if you do what's expedient you have a
short-term conscious goal in mind and
you try to bend everything towards that
end but if you're pursuing what's
meaningful then you just pay attention
to what's going on and you react with
truth and I think that's that's a much
better way of living as far as I'm
concerned it's it's a much more powerful
way of living it means you have to
confront things right then and there
which is I suppose why so many of my
interviews have been in some sense
concert confrontational because people
will impose in a thinking agenda on the
flow of the conversation this is
especially true in the mainstream media
happened again recently with BBC's
HARDtalk that they opposed an agenda in
the conversation and then that just
doesn't work out very well because
I'm paying attention and I will object
to the agenda not because I have a
different agenda except for what I said
which is that I want to say what I think
I want to say as truthfully as I can
what I actually am thinking in this more
abstracted and detached sense and see
what happens so it's it's a hard thing
to clarify because you might say well
dr. Peterson you just said you want to
say what you're thinking but it's not
exactly the same thing it's not like I'm
thinking strategically I'm listening
thoughts II will emerge and I say them
I'm not trying to manipulate I'm not
putting spin on things I'm not trying to
manipulate the conversation in any
particular way and again the reason for
that is because I decided a long time
ago probably thirty years that there was
no more effective way of dealing with a
complex situation than to try to say
what you believe to be true and not to
manipulate it none of that it's just
doesn't because that's all those are all
lies as far as I'm concerned that kind
of manipulation and spin so
if he is invited to the largest possible
number of games is also the person that
goes out to conquer the unknown could
this lie in reciprocal altruism that's a
really good question I would say it
almost certainly does you certainly see
the reciprocal altruism in being invited
to the largest possible number of games
so a little background here it's like
well what's a winner well winner is
someone who wins a game it's like no a
winner is someone who gets invited to
play the largest possible number of
games and that means that you have to be
a good sport and so the good sport is
the winner in the broader game in the
metagame now I put forward the
proposition that the winner of the
metagame is also the person that goes
out to conquer the unknown now let's see
if we can take that apart a little bit
well one of the one of the attributes of
being a good sport let's say is that
you're trying to extend your skill
during the game and so you are
confronting the unknown in the game
because you're trying to get better at
playing the game and then you're also
doing that in a way that's of benefit to
the team and so then you can imagine
that being a team leader in in the meta
game which is the game of extending your
skill across the across the broadest
possible set of games is analogous to
leading a team into the unknown so if
you're gonna go confront the unknown
you're probably not gonna do it alone
although you could and to some degree
you have to be alone but you're
generally gonna do it in a cooperative
and competitive way I mean that's why in
stories like the Lord of the Rings and
The Hobbit for example and even Harry
Potter for that matter none of those
people are alone they they lead or are
part of a broader social group and
they're important and they're team
players within that group so the team
player elements seems to be something
that's common to conquering the unknown
and to reciprocal altruism and and to
being invited to play the largest number
of games the question then is what makes
an effective leader and an effective
leader is someone who's able to
synthesize the group and to lead it
forward towards the goal yeah that's it
and you know in a game obviously the
good player is leading the team forward
to the goal and that's
same in a quest the good player is the
leader who's leading the team towards
the goal so there's a there's a deep
analogy there and it's not just
reciprocal altruism I don't think that's
quite the right terminology though
because there's an element of pragmatic
competence that goes along with it to
you you all you can't merely be willing
to engage in reciprocal altruism to be a
good player or to conquer the unknown
you also have to have skill and
discipline so I would say reciprocal
altruism is necessary but not sufficient
precondition right talent skill ability
all of those things are creativity all
of those things are also important so
that's a bit of an answer to that but
it's a very very good question
so please confirm if you're Harry Potter
patroness Patronus would in fact be a
frog we need answers doctor well you'd
certainly think that wouldn't you a frog
well I think that's obvious it's got to
be a frog or maybe a lobster I wouldn't
I wouldn't have guessed that it would be
a frog but that certainly seems to be
how things have developed and I suppose
you know a frog is at home at home on
dry land and in the water and that makes
the Frog a kind of psychopomp and I've
strived to be at home in the air and in
the water and to bring up the gold ball
from the bottom of the lake like the
Frog Prince yeah yeah definitely frog
okay so you've got your answer I've got
my answer to I guess on completing
understand myself calm I scored
exceptionally low zero on
conscientiousness industriousness and
orderliness
what can I do for motivation well Dean
the first question is how old are you
and you're gonna have an easier life if
you're still young because if you're
older and you have that score then
that's gonna be rough
perhaps you're high in openness in which
case you're going to derive your
motivation from engaging in creative
endeavors
perhaps you're high in agreeableness
which means that you might find meaning
in caring for other people perhaps
extraversion which means you're going to
find engagement in being with other
people so so those are potential sources
of motivation you may have to look
elsewhere then duty let's say and
achievement ambition for your primary
sources of motivation one thing I would
caution you though is that you likely
need to make friends with a scheduler
like Google Calendar try to design days
you want to have and to learn to
structure your time because even if
you're high an openness which makes you
creative yes you're gonna have a hell of
a time sticking to things and so maybe
you need to partner with someone who's I
in conscientiousness but I would really
recommend trying to discipline yourself
you use a use Google Calendar to design
the day's you want to have and learn to
schedule and regulate your time use
because zero is very low and my
suspicions are you'll pay quite a high
price for that so what do you think
about Ellis Miller enter thesis that
most psychological diseases and aberrant
behavior of the result of some kind of
childhood trauma some are but some forms
of childhood trauma are also a
consequence of psychological diseases
and aberrant behavior so this is very
very complicated I'm more on the
existentialist front with regards to
these sorts of theories so Ellis
Miller's thesis is basically Freudian
Freud's thesis Freud certainly posited
that many forms of psychological
distress were a consequence of
childhood trauma of various sorts I
think the existentialist take on that is
more accurate which is that life in and
of itself is sufficiently harsh and full
of betrayal and other forms of
malevolence to cause any number of
psychological diseases and produce any
amount of aberrant behavior so I don't
think it has to be it's not as if we all
had childhoods without trauma that we
would have grown up to be perfect adults
it's that's also a disguised form of
Rousseau and philosophy and the Russos
philosophy is people are basically good
but culture makes them evil and that's
not true people are basically good and
evil and culture fortifies the
possibility of both adds strength to the
possibility of both so I don't I I think
that people are sometimes damaged in
childhood in ways that need to be
addressed in adulthood but that there
are plenty plenty of other reasons for
psychological and physical disorder
genetic causes causes related to all
sorts of physical diseases no it's way
too simple it's way too simple of a
hypothesis and it's caused an awful lot
of trouble because a lot of
simple-minded therapists always assume
that if someone is having psychological
problems in adulthood it must be because
they had childhood trauma and everybody
has an unhappy childhood to some degree
so you can always find something and
often the childhood trauma that they're
looking for has to be sexual and so they
dig and dig until they find or invent
often invent something that you know
allows a single causal attribution and
it's just life just isn't that simple
man there's lots of reasons to be ill
way more reasons to be old than to be
healthy so
what if the truth could unravel your
entire life yeah well first of all it
would and second yeah I know what you
mean
you mean what if I suppose the Cardinal
case there would be that you did
something really terrible and then if
that was revealed it would be a
catastrophic situation it's like without
knowing the details of that I can't
provide a generic answer you know I
think that there are some sins that are
so egregious that you don't get to
confess to them you know like if you've
done something terrible and I'm not
recommending this it's just an example
if you've done something terrible and
you know that if you revealed it it
would blow the lives of many people
around you apart it isn't obvious to me
that you have any moral justification
for confessing just to free your
miserable soul so what if the truth
could unravel your entire life well
maybe you need to go to Catholic
confession and let someone know exactly
what happened so you're clear about it
and then maybe what you need to do is to
swear to whatever God you worship that
you're gonna try to walk the straight
and narrow from here on in and that'll
be sufficient to atone for whatever
terrible thing that you did and that's a
that's a form of prayer and it sounds
like one that you desperately need at
least in principle know so without
knowing the details that's about the
best I can do
I think what put you over with so many
of us was the constructive message of
how to be a good man well a good person
I would say do you think that's where
the media want you to go I don't know
generally not they I mentioned this
earlier is the the media as it
disintegrates and it certainly is
disintegrating at an incredibly rapid
rate everything is political that it's
as if the philosophical and the
psychological and the theological don't
exist
and you know increasingly in my
interviews I've been talking about
what's been happening at my lectures on
my tour and describing the fact that the
vast majority of the audience isn't
there for political reasons at all
they're there because they want to
figure out how to have a responsible and
meaningful life and it's as if that
story just doesn't exist the the
framework which is basically a political
framework and increasingly a politically
correct framework doesn't allow that to
exist as a reality and that's why well
I'm much more comfortable lecturing to
the crowds that have been coming to see
me than I am talking to journalists it's
become I have to I have been limiting my
my interactions with journalists even
though that might not be self-evident
yet I have been trying to do that that
the demands have been increasing so the
proportion of media invitations that I'm
responding to has fallen dramatically
even though the absolute number hasn't
declined as precipitously and the reason
for that is that while I find the I find
the typical interview very stressful
very very stressful I'm on guard and I
would say also my attitude isn't as good
as it could be anymore because I've been
I'm because I'm on guard so much it's
easier for me to get a bit snappy and an
unpleasant and that's bad that's bad I
don't want to do that I want to stay
calm and detached and try to you know
tell the truth and be happy that I'm
there regardless of the circumstances
the fact that the mainstream media let's
say is not
very receptive oh the sometimes there's
exceptions not very receptive to the
idea that I could just be going around
talking to people who want to get their
life together is quite saddening and I
think it's definitely a commentary on
the fundamental corruption of our media
apparatus I think it's better to talk on
YouTube to speak on my podcast to do
these lectures and I think it's
increasingly better to do that the
long-form discussions on YouTube though
with people like Joe Rogan and Dave
Rubin and and so forth that works just
fine so a new media form is emerging and
I think it's going to be a lot more
productive it won't be as scripted it'll
be much longer form it'll be allow for
much more thoughtfulness and I'm but
it's okay it's not like the media
exposure although it's been stressful
it's not like I'm not grateful for it
even people who've put me on the spot
very badly have ended up doing me a
tremendous favor but the problem is is
that because the problem is I'm becoming
too much on guard and and I've noticed a
developing sense of impatience within me
and some suspicion and that's not good I
don't want to be in situations where
those are my fundamental orientations
it's it's a it's a sign of a certain
amount of internal corruption on my part
and I want to be in situations where I'm
speaking with people speaking honestly
to people who are honestly listening
that would be that's a good situation so
would you agree with CS lewis that if
you look for truth you may find comfort
if you look for comfort you will find
despair oh yes that's definitely the
case it's quite an intelligent phrase
because he says if you look for truth
you may find comfort he didn't say you
will find comfort yeah well sometimes if
you look for truth you don't find
comfort to begin with that's for sure
you find a lot of trouble but sometimes
you have to go through a lot of trouble
to get to set things right if you look
for comfort despair well the reason for
that is that you can't look for comfort
in life life isn't about comfort life is
a deadly game it's a game of life and
death
it's a game of good and evil it's
everything's on the line your sanity is
on the line your your freedom from pain
is on the line your freedom from despair
is on the line your family's on the line
there's no comfort life is an adventure
and I think the greatest adventure that
you can possibly have is one is the one
that you find if you look for the truth
and that's a good place to stop that's
been 90 minutes and I've been reasonably
sharp and with it for the full 90
minutes and so I think I'll bring it to
a close just a couple of reminders for
those of you who tuned in late if you
want to try out the self authoring
program I made a code Auguste and that
entitles you to 20% off there's a
two-for-one special so you can give it
to a friend as well if you want to try
understand myself which is a personality
test it only takes about 15 minutes it's
quite a bit easier than the self
authoring suite the code for that is
also August that also gives you 20% off
self-offering helps you read about your
past and present and future and you can
do a bad job and if you haven't
developed a life plan and you don't know
where you are and you don't know where
you're going then I would highly
recommend trying the program and you're
welcome to do a bad job at it because a
bad plan is is a lot better than no plan
at all
understand myself we'll help you
understand who you are for better or
worse and and people have responded
quite positively to it so I think it's
worth the 15 minutes and the 995 that it
costs discounted 20 percent now so I
guess that's about 795 something like
that so that the second Iceland lecture
is going to come out soon I released the
first Iceland lecture which is part of
12 rules for life I have a tour coming
out through the northeastern part of the
United States starting in September and
then over to the UK and northern Europe
in September and October and then
Australia New Zealand in February I've
really enjoyed the tour I think it's an
amazing opportunity it's been
extraordinarily heartwarming let's say
to talk to so many people who are trying
to put their lives together and if
enough people do that then they will put
their lives together and that will help
put everything else together and so
hopefully these QAS are a smart small
part of that so thank you very much for
listening in and I'll try to do one in
September if I don't it's because I'm on
the road all the time but I will
definitely try to do one in September so
thank you for to my patreon supporters I
mentioned to you guys that I am working
hard on the online university and have
hired three people to work on that and
that we're about a year ahead of
schedule I would say where I thought I'd
be so in three months were a year ahead
of where I figured I'd be we'd be so
thanks again good night
ciao